<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Information for James Mclurg late dean of Guild of Edinburgh, George Clerk, Robert Blackwood and others, merchants and tradesmen of Edinburgh against Sir John Hall, Sir Archibald Muir, and others the present magistrates and council thereof.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I164aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504478</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2591:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Information for James Mclurg late dean of Guild of Edinburgh, George Clerk, Robert Blackwood and others, merchants and tradesmen of Edinburgh against Sir John Hall, Sir Archibald Muir, and others the present magistrates and council thereof.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date and place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Sutro Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mclurg, James.</term>
               <term>Clerk, George.</term>
               <term>Blackwood, Robert.</term>
               <term>Hall, John, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Muir, Archibald, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Edinburgh (Scotland). --  Town Council.</term>
               <term>Judges --  Scotland --  Edinburgh --  Election --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>City councils --  Scotland --  Edinburgh --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171794:1"/>
            <head> 
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>emblem of the City of Edinburgh</figDesc>
                  <head>NISI DOMINVS FRVSTRA</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>INFORMATION, For <hi>James M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>lurg</hi> late Dean of Guild of
<hi>Edinburgh, George Clerk, Robert Blackwood,</hi> and others, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and
Tradeſmen of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> againſt Sir <hi>John Hall,</hi> Sir
<hi>Archibald Muir,</hi> and others the preſent Magiſtrats and Council
thereof.</head>
            <p>THe perpetuating of the Magiſtracy and Government of the City of
<hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> in the ſame perſons, or in the Hands of few by Turns,
being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the fundamental Laws and Conſtitutions of the City,
tending not only to the diſcouragment of other well deſerving Citizens, but
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the appropriating and waſting of the Common good, for ſupporting
the privat Intereſt and Ends of ſuch as aim at perpetual Magiſtracy;
theſe Projects and Deſigns have always been moſt unacceptable to the
generality of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants.</p>
            <p>There was never a more open and manifeſt deſign of
perpetuating the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy in the Hands of a few, than at this time, a
particular Faction having continued conſtantly in the Council, and influenced
all the Elections theſe four years bygone; during which time, more Violations
and Invaſions have been made upon the Set, and Conſtitution of the City,
then can be inſtanced in any preceeding Age, and that not only by overturning
and contemning the Laws for regulating the manner of Leeting and Election, but
by groſs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant Gratifications and Donatives, without either cauſe
or pretext, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that during the Influence of this Magiſtracy,
the Good Town loſt the Impoſition upon Malt, which was the greateſt part
of their Revenue, and which was enjoyed and poſſeſt by their
Predeceſſors, with the univerſal conſent of the Inhabitants, the
Brewars, and all who bore the Burden, and thereby was ſo far differenced from
the caſe of the illegal Exactions, diſcharged by the <hi>Claim of
Right,</hi> that the Privy Council upon full Debate did continue the
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats in poſſeſſion thereof, and accordingly they did
poſſeſs it until it was<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171794:2"/>diſcharged and cut off by an
Act of Parliament; and if their Imprudence was not the occaſion of that Act,
at leaſt it muſt be ſaid, that no Donative (whereof ever their
Predeceſſors were poſſeſſed) was diſcharged by any King or
Parliament, except what fell out during their Magiſtracy; yet that Misfortune
did not hinder the exorbitant Gratifications, which were deſigned to
ſupport and advance their Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for which there lyes a Complaint at the
inſtance of the ſame Purſuers before the Lords Commiſſioners of Their
Majeſties Theſaury, againſt theſe who have had the influence of the
Magiſtracy theſe years bygone, and who unwarrantably elicit and delivered
up a Bond for a great Sum of Money, and who to cover their ſhame in
delivering that Bond, do appear before the Theſaury to ſupport it as a
juſt Debt, contrary their Truſt, which doth oblige them to defend the
Common-Good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all unjuſt Burdens and Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>There is ſuch regard due to the Magiſtracy of this
Metropolitan City, that the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of it could not be induced to ſtate any
publick Complaint againſt them upon a few or ſmall Tranſgreſſions;
but finding at laſt that the fundamental Conſtitutions had been utterly
neglected and contemned at three ſeveral ſucceſſive Elections, and that
by theſe Streatches, the Government of the City is now divided betwixt Sir
<hi>John Hall</hi> and Sir <hi>Archibald Muir,</hi> who have ſucceeded by
Turns, and who ſtill continue the ſame perſons upon the Council, that
influenced the former Elections, and who were retained, and acted in the
Council manifeſtly contrary to the Set, and the general Inclination of the
City both Merchants and Trades, and all that were any clog or weight upon them,
being now thrown out of the Magiſtracy &amp; Council. Some of the Neighbours
who joined not in any of their Illegalities, nor were elected to any Office
ſince <hi>Michaelmaſs</hi> 1690, and refuſed to ſit and act with Sir
<hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald</hi> after his Election, until they took a formal
Proteſtation, which the Records bears, that their coming to Council ſhould
not import any approbation of the Election.) Have at laſt been conſtrained
to raiſe a Proceſs before the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, for puniſhing of theſe
who contraveened the ſame, and have entred into the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy by illegal
Elections, and for annulling the laſt Election that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats and
Council of the preceeding year, may proceed to a new legal and formal Election,
excluding only ſuch particular perſons as ſhall be proven guilty, or
acceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Invaſions and Incroachments Libelled.</p>
            <p>This Proceſs being called, the Privy Council were pleaſed to
hear Parties diſtinctly in their own Preſence upon every Article of the
Libel; point by point, and afterwards to allow both Parties to inform upon the
Grounds that were Debated, that the Buſineſs might be diſtinctly
underſtood, and deliberatly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, according to the Weight and
Importance of it.</p>
            <p>The firſt Article of the Libel, is, that Sir <hi>John Hall</hi>
being Elected in <hi>May</hi> 1689, and being bound by Oath in the uſual
form, not to continue above two years in the Office together, was neceſsitate
to dimit in <hi>April</hi> 1691, at which time there appeared a Faction in the
Town Council, who were determined by right or wrong, to advance Sir
<hi>Archibald Muir</hi> to the vacant Office, and albeit that Party had a great
Support at the time, yet the appearance of a Faction, gave early ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion
of the deſign, of perpetuating the Magiſtracy in the hands of a few, and
this procured ſuch Oppoſition to that deſign, that it could not be
brought about with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extraordinary Streatches.</p>
            <p>The ordinary Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> conſiſts of 25
perſons, and the Provoſt or Praeſes doth Vote firſt, and hath a
ſecond Vote in caſe of equality, and the Set requires a Council of thirty
perſons, to be all preſent at the Leeting of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats, and 38 at the
Election, who muſt alſo be all preſent, ſo that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of 30
having power of making Leets, may exclude whom they pleaſe from 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171794:2"/>theſe Leets, and conſequently from the Magiſtracy, and
therefore the great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue of Elections, is the framing of the Council of
30, for whoever is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the plurality of that Council, is by
conſequence Maſter of the Election, by excluding all Competitors.</p>
            <p>The Method of making up the Council of 30, is by calling all to be
preſent, who have Right to Vote in the Leeting, and if any be abſent,
theſe who are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent have power to chuſe others to repreſent the
abſents, and theſe who are Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to fill up the Council are called
Proxies, ſo the Strugle on either hand was to have Proxies Elected favourable
to the deſign of either Party, and upon the matter the plurality of theſe
who were preſent and upon the place, had the true influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to turn the
Election to either ſide.</p>
            <p>It happened that there were only 22 of 30 upon the place, whereby
eight Proxies were to be Elected for filling up the Council of 30.</p>
            <p>The Provoſt having Demitted, the eldeſt Baillie did precede,
and as Praeſes, had the firſt and laſt Vote in caſe of equality; and in
the choiſe of the eight Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies, ſome were elected croſs to the Deſign
of advancing Sir <hi>Archibald,</hi> by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverted plurality, but as to
the greateſt number of Proxies, the Council di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided equally eleven to
eleven, whereby the Praeſes, who did not favour Sir <hi>Archibald,</hi> did
caſt the ballance againſt him, by his odd Vote.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> and his parties hopes being defeated by
loſs of all the Proxies, they proteſted againſt the Praeſes, his taking
an odd Vote, and did withdraw in a moſt irregular and mutinous manner.</p>
            <p>Theſe who remained might have joyned with the eight Proxies
nominat, who being elected, had as good right to act as any other Members of
the Council, and might have elected new Proxies in place of theſe who had
withdrawn; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other deſign, than peace and concord, they rather
chooſed to adjourn the Council to another diet; and to juſtifie their
procedure, did exhibit an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to the Duke of <hi>Hamilton,</hi>
Preſident of the Privy Council, which his Grace having communicat to the
Board, and Anſwers being made to it, both parties were called to debate the
Point anent the right of the odd Vote.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> and his faction, finding themſelves
worſted in the matter of the odd Vote, did take the boldneſs and confidence
to aſſert a manifeſt falſhood at the Council Barr, which was the
foundation of annulling the former Election of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies, and introducing Sir
<hi>Archibald</hi> to the Magiſtracy, and of all the ſtretches in the
following Elections, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Proxies were not at all regularly
Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by either party, in ſo far as two old Counſellours of the former
year, who were upon the place, had right to have concurred with the preſent
ordinary Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which would have made up the number of twenty four, whereby
there was no place for eight, but ſix Proxies to fill up the number of
thirty. This impudent and falſe aſſertion did gain credit with the Privy
Council, who found that the two old Counſellours ought to have been called to
an extraordinary E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, being upon the place; and that no Proxies ſhould
have been choſen for them, unleſs they had refuſed when called; and that
any Election without their being called, was informal and irregular; and
therefore ordained the Magiſtrats and Council to begin a formal Election
<hi>de novo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> and his faction having the advantage of
this unexpected Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, they knew their impudent aſſertion would not
abide a ſecond view; and therefore did peremptorly reſolve to precipitat an
Election before the next diet of Privy Council, and when they were met, to
begin this new and regular Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the firſt ſtep was ſtill to
chooſe the Proxies, for filling up the Council of<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171794:3"/>thirty;
and then they conſidering that the Penalty of tranſgreſſing the Set, is
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy and Incapacity, they durſt not adventure to admit theſe old
Counſellours, as having any proper right to ſit, and Vote with them in the
Election of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proxies; but rather chooſed to throw off the Mask, and
owne to the World, how impudently they had averred a falſehood at the Council
Bar, as if any old Counſellours had a proper right to concur with the
ordinary Council in electing of Proxies; and a <hi>Quorum</hi> of the ordinary
Council of them preſent, did Elect Proxies so fill up the Council of thirty,
in the very ſame way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the former Proxies had been Elected,
without admitting theſe old Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours; So that if the firſt Election
of Proxies was void, the ſecond Election was much more ſo, being after the
Act of Council, founded upon their own aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, and being contrary to,
and inconſiſtent with both; and if the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Proxies was
regular and formal, as truly it was, there was no place for a ſecond Election
of Proxies.</p>
            <p>This being an Important Article, which is the foundation of the
preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, and all the Illegalities that followed; The Purſuers
make uſe of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther probation, than the Town Council Books produced,
wherein is recorded the Information exhibited to the Duke of
<hi>Hamiltoun,</hi> with the Anſwers and Act of Privy Council, annulling the
former Election of Proxies, all in the Sederunt the 5<hi>th</hi> of
<hi>June</hi> 1691 and upon the 6<hi>th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> there is marked
a Sederunt of the ordinary Council, not comprehending theſe old
Counſellours; and in the ſame Sederunt, the ſaid <hi>James Baillie</hi>
and <hi>Patrick Johnſton,</hi> who were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have a proper Right to
joyn with the ordinary Council, and have a Vote in the Election of Proxies, are
Elected Proxies in place of two old Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, which proves the point as
perfectly as any thing imaginable can be.</p>
            <p>It is anſwered, 1. That it appears by the Council Books
produced, that <hi>James Baillie</hi> and <hi>Patrick Johnston,</hi> were
preſent in the Council of thirty, at the Leeting, and in the Council or
thirty eight, at the Election of Sir <hi>Archibald Muir,</hi> and whether they
be marked preſent as Counſellours, or as Proxies, is but a meer niceity,
which the Clerk may not have regarded in the marking of the Council Books; and
it is of no moment, or importance, whether they were there as Counſellours,
or as Proxies, ſeing they were preſent; neither can every ſmall error or
omiſſion be ſufficient to annul an Election, which would leſſen the
au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Magiſtrats.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Election 1691. cannot be quarrelled after ſo long
time, becauſe there hath interveened two Elections; So that the Magiſtrats
then Elected, have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the full time of their Offices, and have now fallen
out by courſe, and by ſuch a conſequence, the Purſuers might run back
to quarrel Elections at any time within the preſcription of fourty years.</p>
            <p>It was Replyed, The Council Books do clearly prove, that the
procedor at Sir <hi>Archibalds</hi> Election, was unſuitable to what he had
aſſerted, and contrary to the Act of Privy Council: And ſeing the Law has
fixed certain Rules in Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for no other end, but to prevent Faction in,
and inhauncing of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy; Theſe Rules ought to have been
preciſely performed, eſpecially when there was ſo equal a Juſtle, that
a Grain weight was ſufficient to caſt the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance; And Sir
<hi>Archibald</hi> thought it no Triffle, to aſſert to the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,
that old Counſellours, who ought to have been called to the Leeting, were
neglected; but when that falſhood did gain credit, and ſerved his turn, he
pleads its now become but a Triffle, though upon that Triffle his Magiſtracy
is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but under his favour, if he hath either aſſerted a Falſhood
to the Privy<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171794:3"/>Council; or if his aſſertion were true, and
yet he had neglected to perform, what both the Privy Council and the Set did
require; he and all who p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omoted
that Election, ought to be moſt ſeverely and examplarly puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas it is pretended, that it is the ſame thing,
whether they be marked preſent as Counſellours or Proxies. The Defenders
are in a wilful miſtake, for the whole intrigue of an Election, is to gain
the plurality of thoſe who have right to Elect the Proxies; and therefore Sir
<hi>Archibald</hi> plead before the Privy Council, that theſe old
Counſellours had right to be Electors of the Proxies; and the Election was
not annulled, becauſe they were not Elected Proxies, but becauſe they were
not called to the Election of Proxies, and they were not ſo called at the
2<hi>d</hi> Election, more than at the firſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whereas it is pretended, That the marking of theſe as
Proxies, may be a miſtake of the Clerk. It is anſwered, (may be) is no
Defence, but truly it is impoſſible to be ſo; for immediatly after the
Act of Privy Council is Recorded upon the fifth, the Sederunt of the ſixth of
<hi>June</hi> begins, which contains all the Members of Council that were then
preſent: Thereafter follows the Acts of that Council; and one of the Acts
thereof was, that they Elected <hi>James Baillie</hi> and <hi>Patrick
Johnſton</hi> to be Proxies, and for a further evidence that it would not
poſſibly be a miſtake, the ſame Sederunt contains a proteſtation
ingroſſed, taken againſt the Council for the time, becauſe they had
walked down-right contrary to the Act of Privy Council in that particular, even
before the Election of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats; ſo they could not pretend
ignorance.</p>
            <p>To the 2<hi>d,</hi> That the Magiſtrats Elected in <hi>June</hi>
1691, are now gone out by courſe before they were quarrelled; and by that
preparative, an Election might be called in queſtion at any time within
preſcription.</p>
            <p>It is Replyed, The Purſuers do not conclude the annulling of
that Election 1691. But do libel theſe Violations and Invaſions upon the
Set, as Crimes pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable in Sir <hi>Archibald,</hi> and theſe who were
acceſſory to that illegal Procedor, and to ſatisfie the Privy Council
that this Magiſtracy has its foundation upon a Falſhood, and that it hath
been continued by a tract of practices, illegal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, that therefore
the laſt Election ſhould only be annulled, and that theſe of the former
Council who had no acceſſion to the foreſaid Violations, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to
a new and formal Election.</p>
            <p>The next Point inſiſted on, was the Precipitation of the
firſt Election, the Act of Council being of the 4. of <hi>June</hi> without
calling or hearing the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies who were legally Elected, the ordinary
Council fell to be upon <hi>Friday</hi> the 5. of <hi>June,</hi> &amp; the Town
Council having continued till after one a clock, the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; a number
with him having withdrawn, the youngeſt Baillie did take upon him to
preſide, &amp; did call an extraordinary Council upon <hi>Saturnday</hi> the
ſixt, where Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies were Elected to fill up the Council of 30, which could
not be found out in all <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> without calling the Towns Servants
and Penſioners, who by the 22. Act of the meeting of Eſtates, were excluded
from Voting in the Election by the Pole, and even theſe could not be had
without Threats and Promiſes, and another extraordinary Dyet was called upon
<hi>Munday,</hi> without the Warrand of the firſt Magiſtrat for the time,
and at that Dyet Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> was both Leet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Elected Provoſt,
whereas the Set appoints the Leeting to be in one day, and the Election in
another, pages 15 and 16. and all this was neceſſary, becauſe both
Council and Seſſion were to ſit the day following, which would have
ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their Procedure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171794:4"/>It was Anſwered, the Privy Council having
appointed a Provoſt to be Elected, it was their duty to proceed with all
convenient Diligence, and tho the eldeſt Baillie did withdraw, he could not
diſſolve the Council without their conſent, and any Magiſtrat may call
a Council, and a <hi>Quorum</hi> being met, they may proceed. 2. There is no
Law or Cuſtom excluding Towns Penſioners from Voting, and theſe who are
aimed at, being perſons who have been in the chief Magiſtracy, they are yet
capable of the ſame Offices, much more to be Proxies, and the Act of the
meeting of Eſtates relates only to that particular Article. 3. The Leeting
and Election of the whole Magiſtrats at <hi>Michaelmaſs</hi> does require
two Dyets, but the Election of a ſingle Magiſtrat at an extraordinary Dyet
does not require the ſame, and the Defenders deny any Threats or
Promiſes?</p>
            <p>It was Replyed, that the three eldeſt Baillies having withdrawn
after one a clock, and after the Council was adjourned to the next ordinary
Dyet, it was a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption without precedent, that the youngeſt ſhould
not only take upon him to act as Praeſes at that Dyet, but alſo to call an
extraordinary Council the next day, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conſtant rule of all
Judicatures that none can call an extraordinary meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, except the Praeſes
or principal Member upon the place, eſpecially in matters of the greateſt
Moment and Importance. 2. The meeting of Eſtates having excluded Towns
Penſioners and Servants from Voting by the Pole, it was incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous and
illegal that ſuch ſhould be admitted as Members in a Council of 30. and the
calling of them, had a tacit Inſinuation of Threatning, in caſe Sir
<hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balds</hi> Election had proceeded without them, ſo that they were
neither at freedom to ſtay away, nor at freedom to Vote when they came,
leaſt they ſhould loſe their Penſions, without which ſeverals of them
could not ſubſiſt, and there were more direct Threatnings uſed
againſt others to force them in, and all this practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, notwithſtanding
of Proteſtations taken, which are alſo recorded in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derant</hi>
of the 6 of <hi>June.</hi> 3. The Leeting and Election in one day, was
unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, and what the Set doth appoint
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is to be obſerved at every
extraordinary Election, unleſs there could be ſome important Reaſon of
Diſparity, otherways all that is appointed by the Set, might be neglected at
an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Election upon that Pretence, for the Set ſuppoſes the
ordinary time of Election, and by that reaſoning, the Defenders might pretend
that there were no need for 30. or 38. perſons, for the Leeting and Election
of a ſingle Magiſtrat, and there is nothing more ſuitable than that the
Leeting and Election ſhould be at different Dyets, becauſe after the Leets
are compleated the Trades who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
of 30. are bound to retire, and meet with the eight extraordinary Deacons in
the <hi>Magdalen</hi> Chappel before the Election, and it were very incongruous
that the Magiſtrats and Merchant Council, ſhould continue to ſit in
Council, when they could Act nothing till the Trades did return.</p>
            <p>And as to the Inſtances of the Leeting and Election of Sir
<hi>Thomas Kennedy</hi> and Sir <hi>Magnus Prince</hi> in one day, that can be
no precedent, becauſe they were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Kings Letter, and there was
only the ſhadow, but not the ſubſtance of a free Election.</p>
            <p>The next point inſiſted in was, that the Set page 10, provides
that none be upon the Council above two years together, except they be
Office-men, or by vertue of their Office be upon the Coucil, and by the Set
<hi>page</hi> 9, <hi>Tit. Council.</hi> It is clear that none are Reckoned
Office-men but the ſeven Magiſtrats, and the reſt of the 25 being 18
Perſons are only Counſellors, and by the Set <hi>page</hi> 8. Tradeſmen
are not Capable to be Magiſtrats or Office-men, yet <hi>George Stirling</hi>
hath been upon the Council ever ſince the Popular Election, albeit
Inſtruments were taken againſt<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171794:4"/>him at
<hi>Michailmaſs</hi> 1691 that he could not be continued: And the like at
<hi>Michaelmaſs</hi> 1692. And he was ſo far convinced of it, that he
acknowledg'd in face of Council the continuing of him was contrary to the Set,
yet the was perſwaded to make bold with it. In like manner <hi>William
Menzies</hi> hath been above two years upon the Council without Office, and
theſe were active Inſtruments in the laſt Election, who ought not at all
to have been Members or concerned in it.</p>
            <p>It was anſwered, the Set prohibiting any to be above two years
upon the Council, contains a quality, <hi>viz,</hi> except they be Office-men,
or by vertue of their Office on the Council, and <hi>George Stirling</hi> and
<hi>William Menzies</hi> are both in the caſe of that exception, for neither
of them were evere above two years together upon the Council in the ſame
Capacity. For Deacon <hi>Stirling</hi> was firſt a Trades Counſellor, then
two years an ordinary Deacon, and then a Trades Counſellor, and now is
continued upon the Council. And in like manner <hi>William Menzies,</hi> was
firſt Treaſurer, and then old Treaſurer, afterwards old Baillie, and
laſtly old Dean of Gild; And ſo changed Offices yearly. 2. Cuſtom hath
cleared this, for <hi>William Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> Tailyor continued Eight years on
the Council, by changing his Character from Deacon to Tradeſ-Counſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or: And <hi>Alexander Reid</hi>
Gold-Smith was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the ſame way upon the Council Seven years; And
the Purſuers miſtake is in this: that they do not canſider a Deacon as an
Office, whereas ordinary Deacons are certainly by their Office upon the
Council, and ſo <hi>George Stirling</hi> falls under the exception of the
Set.</p>
            <p>It was Replyed that the Defenders gave ſo much Proof of their
Ingenuity in the former Pleading anent the Odd Vote, that the Purſuer cannot
be afraid that the privy Coucil will be eaſily Impoſed upon, to take their
Commentare upon the Set as good Corn, and what is now pretended, is juſt as
Falſe and abſured as the Old Aſſertion of the Rights of old
Counſellors to Vote at extraordinary Elections; And this Commentare upon the
Set would utterly enervat and overturn the whole Deſign of it, which is to
Exclude the poſſibility of Inhancing Magiſtracy, for at this Rate; The
Bulk of the Council might continued for life by changing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters once in
Two years: and the thereby be abſolutely Maſter of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the
Exception would be juſt als large as the Rule.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As this conſequence were moſt abſurd, ſo the
Commentare deſtroys the Text, for neither of the the two Defenders fall under
the Exception of Perſons that may be continued above Two years, and it is
abſolutely falſe that either of them are Office-Men, or upon the Council by
Vertue of their Office.</p>
            <p>For clearing of this Important point, the meaning of the word
Office-Men, is expreſt <hi>Page</hi> 9. Title Council, bearing that the
Council doth conſiſt of 18. Perſons, beſide the Office-Men to wit
Provoſt, Bailies, Dean of Guild and Treaſurer, who are the ſeven
Magiſtrats: ſo that Office-Men and Magiſtrats are the ſame thing, and
the ſeven Magſtrats with the 18. Counſellors make the Number of 25; And
it is a mighty meaſure of conſidence to pretend that an ordinary Deacon, or
an old Baillie, or old Dean of Guild, is an Office-Man or more than a
Counſellor, ſeeing this is expreſly contrair to the ſaid <hi>Page</hi>
9. Title Council, which doth not only expreſs the Number of the Council, but
ſet down the Perſons that make up that Number of 18. <hi>viz.</hi> Old
Provoſt, four old Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, old Dean of Guild and Theaſurer, and three
Merchants mo, with eight Craftſ-men, whereof ſix Deacons and two other
Craftſ-men, commonly called Tradeſ-men counſellors; And the Purſuer
deſires to know if either o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
two Complained upon, were in other Capacitie than theſe, that are contained
in the enumeration of the Council, except the time that <hi>William
Minzies</hi> was Theaſurer, which the Purſuers do not reckon or Complain
on.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:171794:5"/>3. Whereas it is pretended, that at the
leaſt, the two Defenders, by vertue of their Office, were upon the Council,
and ſo they fall under the latter part of the Exception. It is anſwered,
this is another quibble in the vain hopes that the Set will be miſtaken; and
though that one miſtake ſhould overthrow the whole intent of it, the
Defenders make no matter. But for clearing the meaning of that part of the
Exception; The import of theſe words, (or by vertue of their Office be upon
the Council) is ſuch as are upon the Council without Election, and that is
the ſeven old Magiſtrats, for theſe who are Magiſtrats this year, are
old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats the next year of courſe, by their Office without Election,
as appears by the Set, page 9. and more fully by the two year Act ſubjoined
to the Set, page 4. which is annually confirmed by Oath, and there is no other
can enter into, or remain upon the Council without Election, or by vertue of
their Office, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the old Magiſtrats allanerly: And whereas it is
pretended, that <hi>VVilliam Meinzies</hi> was an old Magiſtrat, and
<hi>George Stirling</hi> as an ordinar Deacon was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Council. It was
anſwered, none of them were upon the Council by vertue of their Office, but
by Election; for albeit the preſent Magiſtrats of this year, continue upon
the Council the next year without Election; yet if any of them be advanced to a
higher Office, or die, or demit, in that caſe, there is a vacancy of an old
Magiſtrats place, which muſt be ſupplyed by Election, as in this caſe
<hi>VVilliam Meinzies</hi> was advanced to be old Baillie, on the deceaſe of
<hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas VVyllie;</hi> and although <hi>Thomas</hi> would have been old
Baillie of courſe by his Office; yet <hi>VVilliam Menzies</hi> cam there by
Election, and cannot by changing his Character be perptuat in the Council by
ſeveral Elections; In like manner it is a rare pretence, that <hi>George
Stirling</hi> by his Office of ordinary Deacon is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Council, for it is
Council that Elects him an ordinary Deacon, and he is not an ordinary Deacon
without Election; But the Trades do make choice of fourteen Deacons: And out of
theſe, the Council doth choiſe ſix ordinary Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and the Councils
choiſe hath this reſtriction by the Set, that they cannot by Election
continue any Perſon above two years a ſingle Counſellor, but if a
Counſellor be advanced to the Magiſtracy which a Crafts-man cannot, he may
be advanced the third year, and may a fourth year be an old Magiſtrat, and
ſo may advance to a higher degree of the Magiſtracy, till at laſt he go
out. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſeveral Precedents are condeſcended upon, which are
alledg'd to Introduce a Cuſtom of continuing Perſons longer than two years
upon the Council. It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, the Examples are only two, not
ſufficient to Introduce a Cuſtom, and a practiſe contrair to the Set, can
be no Rule to overturn what is clearly provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, and it cannot be
condeſcended upon, that ever Proteſtations were taken againſt theſe
Perſons, or that their continuing was approven by any Judicature, and it is
not every Violation of the Set, that draws Perſons to a publick Complaint
againſt a Magiſtracy, it is true ſome Magiſtrats may have
tranſgreſſed againſt it in one particular, and ſome in another: But
this Magiſtracy hath trampled upon, and invaded it on all corners, and the
Meeting of Eſtates having a ſpecial regard to the Impoſing of
Magiſtrats by an undue Election, did ſtate that as an Article in the claim
of Right to be contrair to Law, and did once appoint Popular Elections that
Magiſtracy might ever proceed by a legal and due Election in time coming. So
that no Precedent before the Poll, can be ſuſtained againſt the
Conſtitution of the City.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171794:5"/>Another notable Violation of the Set was at the
laſt two Elections, in ſo far as the Set appoints 30 perſons to be
preſent at Leeting, and expreſſes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and diſtinct
Capacities of each of theſe 30 perſons, <hi>pages</hi> 14, and 15. and
appoints the ſaid 30 perſons, with eight Craftſmen more, to be preſent
at the Election; yet Deacon <hi>Carſe</hi> and Deacon <hi>Stirling</hi> were
elected, each in two diſtinct Capacities, the one an extraordinary Deavon and
Trades-counſellor, and the other, to wit, Deacon <hi>Stirling</hi> an old
Counſellor, and a new Counſellor at the ſame time; and becauſe the Set
provides 30, and 38 to be preſent at Leeting and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<hi>reſpectivè,</hi> therefore two Proxies were choſen, one for
Deacon <hi>Carſe,</hi> and another for <hi>George Stirling,</hi> though they
were both perſonally preſent.</p>
            <p>It was Anſwered, There is nothing in the Set to hinder any
perſon to be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in two ſeveral Capacities, and particularly to hinder
an extraordinary Deacon to be a Tradeſ-counſellor, or a
Tradeſ-counſellor one year to be continued ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that does not
abridge the number of theſe who Leet and Elect, becauſe Proxies are
choſen to make up that number.</p>
            <p>It was Replyed, This is alſo altogether againſt the Set, for
it doth not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the number of perſons, but likewiſe doth
expreſs their ſeveral Capacities, and if one might ſupply two Capacities,
the number of the Council might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged to the one half; as for example,
if <hi>George Stirling</hi> being a Trades-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor the laſt, might
alſo be continued this, by the ſame reaſon the other Trades-counſellor
might be continued, and likewiſe the three Merchant-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, and ſo
5 of the old Council would be alſo 5 of the new, notwithſtanding the Set,
page 15 provides that the new Council of 18 perſons, and the old Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of
12 ſhall meet for the making of Leets, and by this means the old Council,
will be reduced to ſeven perſons, ſo that it is clear that the Set doth
provide the 12 and 18 to be different and diſtinct perſons to prevent
Packing, and whereas it is pretended, that 5 Proxies may be choſen to
ſupply the place of the old Trade or Merchant Counſellors, it is
anſwered, that does not at all take off the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, for by the Set
the full number are once to be choſen of diſtinct ſeveral perſons, and
the abſence of any Party is to be ſupplied by Proxies, but that there
ſhould be a want in the Conſtitution, and in place of 38 there ſhould be
only 33, or a ſmaller number elected upon the Council, that would intirely
enervat the Set. 2. The ſupplying theſe wanting perſons by Proxies, doth
not at all anſwer the deſign of the Set; for theſe who have the Plurality
of the ordinary Council, can chuſe Proxies as they pleaſe, with proſpect
to the particular deſign in hand, and ſo are abſolutely Maſters of any
Election, and if this were once allowed, a factious Party would always abridge
the number, that they might fill them up, upon a particular proſpect; and the
gaining of one Vote, is moſt ordinarly to gain all the Election, and one Vote
of the Trades is worth two of the Merchants, becauſe the Trades being
incapable of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they are ordinarly invidious and jealous of
inhauncing the Government, and with great difficulty can they be pacqued, and
therefore the Set allows them a greater Intereſt at Election than at any
other time, they begin ordinarly leſs than the third, and at the Election
they are 18 of 38, and by immemorial cuſtom they do abſolutely rule and
influence Elections by the <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Chappel, for they are allowed to
meet ſeparatly there and to Vote upon the Leets of every Magiſtrat, and who
ever hath the plurality of Votes, the ſmaller part by immemorial cuſtom
doth join with the greater, whereby they have 18 uniform Votes at the Election,
and by gaining two of the Merchant-Council, they have the Plurality, ſo that
if a pacquing Magiſtracy ſhould be allowed to abridge the number of Trades,
till the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171794:6"/>did occur, the Merchants in the ordinary
Council, (who are eaſily ſwayed by advancement into the Magiſtracy) and
who have the greateſt influence in it, would chuſe Proxies for Trades one
or moe for the purpoſe, and it would be no difficulty to gain the plurality
of the Trades in the Chappel, and thereby to carry the whole Election.</p>
            <p>And as to the Alledgance that the like has been practiſed
before, There is only a ſingle Caſe inſtanced at the time when Elections
were not free, which can make no Rule.</p>
            <p>Conſtant Cuſtom hath prevailed to give the <hi>Magdalen</hi>
Chappel the over-ruling power of Elections, wherein no great Inconveniency hath
ever been found, but at the laſt Election the major part being againſt Sir
<hi>John Hall,</hi> ſeven of 18 that were for him, did combine, and enter
into a written Ingagement that they ſhould adhere to him, which is a
Practiſe without precedent contrary to Law, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict Utility, tending
only to Faction, and this point being ſimply denyed, it is proven by the
Oaths of the Subſcribers, all of them having acknowledged the Signing of a
Paper, predetermining them as to the Election.</p>
            <p>The Set alſo appoints, page 16. that the Council of 30 ſhould
ſolemnly proteſt before God, that they ſhall chuſe without Fead, Favour
or Colluſion, and the ſecret Practiſes for carrying on this Election
being known, it was required that every Member ſhould be appointed to
proteſt in the Terms of the Set, which was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely refuſed, and
Inſtruments taken thereupon, and it is falſe which is pretended, that ever
Baillie <hi>Blackwood</hi> did acquieſce, elſe the Inſtrument would not
have been inſert.</p>
            <p>The Proxies not having anſwered expectation at the laſt
Election, they were removed by a Vote of Council, and tho the eight
extraordinary Deacons were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, yet they were not admitted to Vote
either, whether they ſhould be removed, or who ſhould be choſen in their
places, becauſe none of them were for the preſent deſign.</p>
            <p>It was anſwered. 1. Proxies have only a precarious Right, and
being choſen only for a particular effect, they might be removed and new ones
choſen at every Dyet. 2. The extraordinary Deacons had no Intereſt to Vote
anent the Proxies, becauſe they have only Right to Vote in the Election.</p>
            <p>It was Replyed. 1. It is true Proxies are only choſen to a
ſpecial effect but that effect is all that relates to the Election, and they
have as good right to act and vote in relation to it, as any other in the
Council, it is true they are but Proxies for ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent perſons, &amp; if the
perſons whom they repreſent ſhould appear at the Dyet they are elected or
any other, they had no more Intereſt, but in abſence of theſe for whom
they are Proxies, they cannot be removed, and they never were removed in any
caſe. 2. The Set appoints 30 perſons for Leeting, and the <hi>Title
Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> page 16. doth provide that the ſaids 30 perſons with 8
extraordinary Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall Elect, ſo the ſame 30 who have Right to Leet,
are alſo to Elect, and cannot be removed, and it is without all precedent to
remove Proxies once cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and in this caſe the Proxies upon the firſt
Election, had already attended two Dyets, and were cited to attend the third at
the Election, tho they were remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when they came. 3. The Set, page 17.
appointing the 8 extraordinary Deacons to be preſent at the Election, they
are a part of the Council that day, and nothing can be Voted in that Council,
whereof they are a part, without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them a Vote, yet they were not
ſuffered to Vote anent the Proxies, and if they had they would have retained
them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171794:6"/>The Set doth alſo provide that none ſhall
be advanced to the Magiſtracy, unleſs they have been one year or two upon
the Council before, yet <hi>Patrick Johnston</hi> was Elected a Baillie at the
Election 1691, and <hi>James Bowden</hi> at the laſt Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tho neither
of them was ever a year upon the Council.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was pretended, that <hi>annus ceptus procompleto
habetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is anſwered, the Set bears, they ſhall be a year or two,
which muſt at leaſt import that they have been one intire year upon the
Council.</p>
            <p>And ſeing the Purſuers have only raiſed this Complaint as
faithful Burgeſſes, for the Preſervation of the Fundamental Laws and
Conſtitutions of the City, without any by end or project of advancing any of
themſelves into the Magiſtracy, but that there may be a free Election of
ſuch perſons as may be acceptable to the people, and ſuch as may be
moſt fit for ſupporting the Intereſt and Government of the Church and
State as they are by Law eſtabliſhed, and that all of the Purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did
very early evidence their Loyalty and Affection to both, and particularly when
this Nation was threatned with a moſt unnatural Invaſion, they are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
Confident that the Lords of their Majeſties Privy Council will be careful to
preſerve the Priviledges and Conſtitutions of this Metropolitan City, and
puniſh the perſons Guilty of, and Acceſſory to the foreſaid
Violations and Invaſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Set and Decreet Arbitral, and annul the
laſt illegal and informal Election, and Authorize the Magiſtrats and
Council, in Office before <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs</hi> laſt, to begin a new and
formal Election, excluding always theſe who have been Acceſſory to the
foreſaid Invaſions, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>John Hall,</hi> Sir <hi>Archibald
Muir, William Menzies, George Stirling, Patrick Haliburton,</hi> and
<hi>Patrick Johnſtoun,</hi> and the ordinary Deacons who have been
acceſſory to the Combination.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
